Register of the Siegfried Oppenheim papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Siegfried Oppenheim papers
1934-1952
Oppenheim, Siegfried.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (3.1 linear feet)
2000C27
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, orders and other military documents, photographs, and miscellany, relating to American military operations in China at the end of World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Norwood F. Allman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Oliver J. Caldwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
William J. Donovan Memorial Foundation records, Hoover Institution Archives
J. Arthur Duff papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Carl Frederick Eifler papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Suzanne Norman Malloch papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Gilbert Stuart memoirs, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Siegfried Oppenheim, who was a master sergeant assigned to the Office of Strategic Services from 1945 to 1949, was born in Germany in 1909 and attended Columbia University. He worked as a stenographer in New York, serving at the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner in the Bronx and Bellevue Hospital.
Oppenheim enlisted with the United States military after the attack on Pearl Harbor, and in 1942 became a confidential stenographer with Major General Thomas A. Terry of the Second Service Command. He worked in the Police Department of the Military Service Bureau in New York, and was promoted to the rank of staff sergeant from court stenographer in September 1943. He was stationed at Camp Hood, Texas, in 1944 and 1945.
Oppenheim began his work for the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in 1945. He was stationed in China starting in 1945, and continued his work for the OSS after the end of World War II. He also performed duties for External Survey Detachment #44 of the United States Navy. Oppenheim died in 1998.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document the military career and family life of Siegfried Oppenheim. Materials include correspondence, orders and other military documents, photographs, and miscellany related to American military operations in China at the end of World War II.
The collection contains correspondence that Oppenheim sent and received during his service in World War II. Much of the correspondence is with his mother, Regine, and his brother, Irving. In their letters, the Oppenheims discuss family matters, Siegfried Oppenheim's work at the Office of Strategic Services, his experiences in China, and the procurement and shipment of various items.
Photographs in the collection include images of China and the Oppenheim family.
United States. Office of Strategic Services.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.
- Advertisements and menus, undated (Folder 1: 1)
- Alien registration booklet of Tillie Hopfenmain, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  General note
  Aunt of Siegfried Oppenheim
- Booklet for United States personnel in China, 1945 (Folder 1: 3)
- Certificates from physicals, medical clearance, 1945 (Folder 1: 4)
- Changchun House Haunting Company, joke advertisement, undated (Folder 1: 5)
- Clippings, 1945-1952, undated (Folder 1: 6)
- Correspondence (Box 1-4)
  - General, incoming letters (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes letters from Bill Braden, Lewis Byrns, Chao Chih-Ke, Joe Dooley, F. T. Farrell, Vincent R. Fiore, Harrison Hsia, Michael A. Lyons, Herbert Naas, William Rauch, Mary Lou Richardson, Rhea S. Schneider, and Frank Wernimont
    - Undated (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1942 (Folder 1: 8)
    - 1943 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1944 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1945 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1946 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1947 (Folder 1: 13)
    - 1948 (Folder 1: 14)
    - 1950 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 1951 (Folder 1: 16)
    - 1952 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Dupraw, Martin J. (Box 1)
    - Incoming letters, 1943-1944 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Outgoing letters, 1943 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Oppenheim, Irving G. (Box 1)
    - Incoming letters, 1943, 1945-1948 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Outgoing letters, 1944 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Oppenheim, Regine (Box 2-4)
    - Incoming letters (Box 2-3)
      - Undated (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1945 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1946 (Folder 2: 4-7)
      - 1947 (Folder 3: 1-3)
      - 1948 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Outgoing letters (Box 3-4)
      - Undated (Folder 3: 5)
        Scope and Contents note
        Fragment
      - 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 6)
      - 1946 (Folder 4: 1)
      - 1947 (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1948-1949 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Letters to Regine Oppenheim from others, 1934-1939, 1951 (Folder 4: 4)
- Drawing of Irving Oppenheim, undated (Folder 4: 5)
- Instructions for ditching a plane, undated (Folder 4: 6)
- Inventory for shipping, 1946 (Folder 4: 7)
- Invitations, 1947-1948, undated (Folder 4: 8)
- Memoranda, 1945, 1952 (Folder 4: 9)
- Miscellany, 1922, 1942, undated (Folder 4: 10)
- Notice to report for active duty, 1942 (Folder 4: 11)
- Notices, 1948 (Folder 4: 12)
- Notices of classification, 1942 (Folder 4: 13)
- Office of Strategic Services bulletins and circulars, 1945 (Folder 4: 14)
- Orders, 1942-1949 (Folder 4: 15)
- Pay record, receipts, and other financial documents, 1945-1949, undated (Folder 4: 16)
- Photographs, 1936-1949, undated (Box 5)
  Includes photographs of Oppenheim family, including Irving Oppenheim, and images of buildings, landscapes, and street scenes in China, including in Kunming and Shanghai. Includes photographs of American and Chinese military officials and troops. Housed in oversize box.
- Property turn-in slip, 1947 (Folder 4: 17)
  For External Survey Detachment #44
- Subject file (Box 4)
  - Retirement, 1942, 1952 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Training, 1951-1952 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Veterans of Strategic Services, undated (Folder 4: 20)
- Typing assignment, undated (Folder 4: 21)
- Windbag issue, 1945 (Folder 4: 22)
  Published by Special Services Office